This is, uh, my kitchen table and also
my filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor.
The highest calling of mankind I've
often thought was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
Oh, well, I watch your interviews cause
I know how to do it.
I've learned in doing my interviews how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much you wanted.
He said 250.
I said, fine, I didn't negotiate with
him.
I didn't know due diligence till I have
something I'd like to sell and how they
stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world.
Is that right?
One of the most legendary corporate
founders of a company in the United
States the last 50 years was Fred Smith.
He started Fedex.
When he got ready to retire, he picked
one of his 400,000 employees to succeed
him.
The employee is Raj Subramaniam, who is
an Indian immigrant, a graduate of
Syracuse, and somebody who had a chance
to sit down with recently to talk about
what it's like to run Fedex and to
succeed the legendary Fred Smith.
So in the old days, 25 years ago,
somebody wanted to send a letter
overnight, make sure it got there.
I would do a Fedex.
And you, you know, you package it up and
you send.
And I would get there the next day.
But today with the internet, do you
really have many letters going overnight
to people?
No.
My letters are a very, very small piece
of the business.
And I think you send some letters.
So thank you about that.
But it's, uh, if you, if you open up,
uh, our airplanes and look at them, you
imagine we can fill it up with letters.
That's a lot of letters.
So, um, it's actually, you know, we we
move the high value economy of the
world.
In fact, the last year, we moved roughly
$2 trillion worth of goods across the
world.
And they are pharmaceuticals, aerospace,
defense, you know, into textiles.
You just think about the ones.
The value per pound of something is very
high.
They usually go in our system.
How do you envision your business
growing in terms of more customers?
Uh, you've got a pretty good business
already.
How where are you going to take a market
share from UPS or from new entrance to
the field?
Well, I think the market itself is
growing.
And I think, you know, I feel like our
industry that what we do as an industry
is pretty significant and somewhat, you
know, underappreciated actually, because
it's been taken for granted.
It's pristine now in this day and age,
what we do as an industry, whether it is
like it's a 2 or 3 players that we have,
is I think there's a lot of value.
And within that, I think the market
itself is going to grow.
The opportunity for players who really
have standout capabilities in this is
now significant.
And I think I'm confident in our value
proposition that we can compete very
effectively and win share as well.
And how many trucks do you have
delivering all these things?
We have 200,000 motorized vehicles
around the world.
And are you going to have any trucks
that are driverless that some we already
have in.
Uh, we are, you know, working with a
partner in Texas where we have
autonomous driving being tested, and
we'll see how that goes.
Yeah.
Uh, there was a packages get there
quicker or slower?
Well, no, it's the same speed.
The the important thing is the
infrastructure we already have.
We have 638 facilities right on the
highway.
So we can go facility the facility on
the highway and then can be a human
driver.
So that is important component of this
because you know, you don't I don't
think we are yet able to see an
autonomous truck driving down the street
outside here.
How is your business going to change
with AI?
Is I going to make it easier or harder
for your business is going to be great,
because the fact that I told you we have
two petabytes of data every single day,
we realized back in 2020 that the data
that we generate is a valuable asset on
his own.
So we had gone about, you know, really
engineering and creating a platform
using our data on growing a digital twin
or Fedex.
And then comes the revolution in AI.
And then suddenly that now we're able to
use that eye to now supercharge our
data.
So of course we are going to use to
improve our efficiency, our network
efficiency and so on.
That's that's great.
We'll do that.
That's that's the base layer.
But we are also using it to
differentiate and create new value for
our customers.
So they ship more packages.
And uh, when they ship more packages,
they'll know I delivering packages.
That's done more jobs.
In fact, last year we've added about
29,000 jobs in America.
You know, we are also looking at how do
we use the insights that we have to, you
know, orchestrate global supply chain.
So we are you know, there's opportunity
for us to leverage the insights that we
have from our data and do different
things with it.
Now, with all the data that you have,
you've got as much data as any company.
And where the US economy is.
Do you see a recession anywhere in the
near future?
I'm more optimistic versus stealth.
uh, industrial, um, um, growth in this
economy that's coming up.
And we're seeing growth in the B2B
sector.
We'll see how it goes.
But, uh, you know, we if you go back
from September 2022 to next three and a
half years, uh, the industrial, um, the
ISM index was down pretty much 35 to 36
months.
It was a very tough time.
But I think we're starting you know,
there's probably some I mean, if I say I
have a package, I want to deliver it to
the Middle East right now.
Uh, can you deliver packages in the
Middle East because of the war going on
there?
Do you?
Is that a problem for you?
Yeah.
Short answer is we can we have a large
hub in Dubai and, uh, obviously we can
fly Fedex airplanes into Dubai or we
have an operation into Riyadh.
So those things know we can fly, but we
have now I'm using other carriers to
move traffic in and out of Middle East's
operational, but not the same way that
it was before.
So today, what do you want to accomplish
the most?
We have changed our focus very clearly,
and when we had the Investor Day, uh,
back in February, you know, we, we laid
out of goals of a 4% revenue growth,
which is, you know, modest by historical
standards.
Uh, but something again, focused on
those high value verticals, but
generate, you know, 14% bottom line
growth because of okay, here because of
the transformations that we're doing and
generate, you know, $6 billion of free
cash flow.
So that's our financial those are our
financial anchors that we have.
So I noticed that when you are sometimes
you have brought the pandas to the
National Zoo and you've shipped some
back.
Um, is that a for a profitable business
mean that was.
They are the VIPs.
Uh, very important pandas.
Uh, so, uh, you know, this is something
that we have done for some time now.
And because we can do it, uh, you know,
we have done, I think, 15 or so pandas
and we are looking at another one in, in
from Atlanta as well.
So that's something that we do, uh, and
uh, we have you know, we have actually
the delivery of the plane was called the
Panda Express.
And you do other animals like elephants
or things like that.
Well, you know, we used to do animal
charters, by the way, before, but right
now this is a more of a, let's call it
diplomatic move.
What is the biggest challenge that Wall
Street sees you as having as a company,
what Wall Street analysts are always
wanting more revenue, more profits.
What does Wall Street mostly say that
you should be doing that you're not yet
doing?
You know, some of the investors are
frustrated, uh, about, you know, lack of
generation of free cash flow, for
example.
But it have to have investments in
capital to get the network that we have
built so far.
So the fact that we're here and we are
turning a corner and then, you know, I'm
not anticipating at this point going to
moon or Mars, um, you know, we have this
planet pretty much covered, and the
investments that we need are more
incremental at this point.
I think that realization is starting to
sink in.
And so maybe the frustration is starting
to ebb somewhat.
And I think we also have the job to do
then to put points on the board and
demonstrate success on a consistent
basis on this foundation.
I think we'll be right.
And let's go through how you became the
CEO.
So where were you born?
I was born in India in a small state of
Kerala, India, right on the southern
side, the Florida of India.
And were you always interested in and,
uh, distribution as a boy or something,
or
I would know what that was.
Uh, no, it was, uh, very
straightforward, you know.
Uh, middle class childhood focused
heavily.
And luckily for me, education plus
sport, sports is very important in my
life.
So, uh, where you want a big athlete or
something?
I was pretty good.
We were in cricket, cricket and
badminton and athletics.
Everyone knew how good education was.
A ticket to success.
So you're in India, in the Florida of
India, and you decide you want to go to
a cold weather college.
Syracuse.
How did you wind up in Syracuse?
A very good school.
But how did you wind up there?
Well, first of all, you know, you you
have to you have to imagine a world
where there was no Google or information
was, let's say, much scarcer.
So there was a well-worn path.
You go, you know, in India, you know,
those.
You get into the Indian instead of
technology, very competitive school.
And once you get through that, there was
usually a path to get a scholarship to
come to America.
And, uh, you just get all you get really
information is about rankings of uh, top
20 schools in America and.
And Syracuse was in the top 20 for
chemical engineering at the time.
I got a scholarship.
Well, two ranks below, which also got a
scholarship was Florida.
Oh.
So and I don't because this was two rank
zero.
I took Syracuse and I remember going to
the consulate in Mumbai and Bombay at
that time.
And the lady says, you know, it's going
to be cold over there.
And I said, yeah, call whatever.
And now you're the number.
I had not seen temperatures below 75
degrees in my life.
Had you ever seen.
So when I got this.
No, no.
No chance.
So I got to Syracuse the first day and
walking to school, it was 70 degrees and
sunny and everyone's telling me, nice
day and I'm freezing.
So, uh, it went downhill from there.
Did you ever consider transferring when
you saw snow?
It's kind of kind of crazy because by
the time the next six months came
around, my blood was thick.
I was like, even 45 degrees.
I was in my t shirt today.
Actually, I can deal with cold pretty
good.
So you graduated.
Did you say I want to be the CEO of
Fedex?
Or what did you want to do when I joined
Fedex in 91?
And, uh, I barely
knew Memphis.
I didn't know anybody in Memphis.
If someone had told me that this is a
job I would be doing, then I would have
said out a much better chance to play
for the Indian cricket team.
So how did you get the job?
You just interviewed for a job after
college to get my MBA.
I was in I was in campus in Austin,
Texas is kind of the story around it,
too.
I was, um, so I came home one afternoon
and my apartment meter's on the phone
and he's basically on the phone, so I
can do that.
Um, you know, we just leave.
I was leaving the country, so I said,
who's on the phone?
He said, that's Fedex.
He said, they're, you know, coming to
campus.
We want to interview him.
And, um, so but he's not going to be
there.
So I said, give me the damn phone, you
know.
So I call over and I say,
uh, you know, you just talked to my
roommate, but he's not going to be
there, but I'm going to be here.
Can I see my resume?
I send them over?
I said, okay, come on over for the
interview.
So now this is a time when recession
was, you know, pretty deep in 91.
And also I didn't have a green card.
And that's all that's become that has
become an issue from other interviews.
So when I got to the interview, my
euphoria had already come back down
again.
So I see these two gentlemen, very nice
people across the table.
And I say, I didn't say good morning.
I didn't say hello.
I said, I don't have a green card.
I said, if that's a problem, then let
you know, I don't want to waste your
time or mine.
And they look at me like, what is a
strange kid?
And they and say, son, let's first
figure out whether you have what it
takes to do a job at Fedex.
And let's worry about the paperwork.
And then I tell you, I got hired and
that's necessary.
What what was your job?
I was the associate marketing analyst
for international marketing at Fedex.
It can go lower.
Uh, uh, for the staff position, though.
All right.
So you what year was that?
That was 91.
All right, so you work your way up home
a series of jobs, and eventually you
became the, uh, the the president, our
chief operating officer.
Well, yeah, in 2019, I was the president
and CEO of Fedex.
Okay.
Yeah.
So you're president and CEO and Fred
Smith, the legendary founder, is going
to be
there forever.
And people thought, uh, did he call you
one day and said, guess what?
I want you to be my successor.
One day he calls over and says, um, I'm
I'm going to Los Angeles tomorrow.
I looked at your calendar.
You're doing nothing.
Uh, I want you on the plane with me.
And, uh, so it was, I think the day
before Valentine's Day or whatever it
was.
So, um, I'm.
I'm there, you know, and then he.
So he walks into the plane and we go
even before he sits down in terms of
answers.
So would you like to be the president
and CEO of Fedex?
And I'm looking at him as a I'll be
honored, sir.
And he sat down for the next because we
can't get out anymore because, you know,
we got a 4.5 hour flight.
And so you became the president and CEO.
Yeah.
And then how many years later before you
became a CEO?
Uh, three years.
I mean, you become the CEO.
Um, you say to Fred, look, uh, it's a
nice company you built, but I want to
make some changes.
Dramatic changes.
Was that a hard to do?
Because you made a lot of dramatic
changes?
Well, no, Fred was very, very clear
about this.
This is the greatest thing about Fred.
And, I mean, I mean, I'm just going to
call myself one of the very, very
fortunate persons on this planet that I
have spent so much time with them.
You know, it was, uh, very, very clear
that once the mantle shifted over, that.
Okay, you know, we'll give you all the
input we want, but the decision making
was mine.
That meeting with him lasted about two
minutes.
All right, so when you became the CEO,
uh, one of the things you did was to
focus on profitability.
And one of the ways you did that is you
began to, um, I guess, consolidate some
of the divisions.
Can you explain?
There were four divisions at Fedex.
Yeah.
So we were set up in a way to operate
independently with multiple operating
companies and also multiple networks.
So for four parts, write Fedex express,
Fedex ground, Fedex freight and we had
Fedex office and things like that.
But the three main companies, the main
thing was in the United States, there
was a reason why it was set up this way.
And again, we talked about, you know, we
were started off in the Air Express
business, in the ground parcel business.
We were tiny at the turn of the century.
We are only 10% market share.
So we had to make inroads and we need to
be a differentiated play.
So that's what you know.
You know, it took we basically, you
know, grew our market share for many,
many, many years in a row.
But the profile of the traffic was
changing and we needed to consolidate or
networks.
So that was the impetus.
It was an evolution really.
And so the time had come to do that, and
I don't think there was any debate
whether we should do it or not.
You know, so so we started moving in
this direction.
So we consolidated networks,
consolidated the operating companies
into one Fedex.
And we are.
You know this is a is a it's a long
process.
So the consolidations occurred.
And I think the market capitalization is
up about 63%.
The stock is up 73%.
But the revenues are roughly flat.
Well it's a that's not the way it works
because at the turn of the I don't know,
2019, before the pandemic, we were about
$69 billion in revenue.
The next two years we grew 25 billion.
So we got 94 billion, right?
Then it went down to 88.
The shadow of the pandemic.
And now we are back.
So when you say we are back, yes.
But if you look at the longer picture,
we have grown about 5% since about 2019
or 6% figures for us, part of the
culture that Fred drilled into our brain
is that change is the only constant.
And if you don't like change, you will
absolutely hate extinction.
Your parents are in their early 90s.
And do they call you and say they're
proud of you?
They're very, very proud.
And they could not have imagined
anything close to close to this.
Uh, and so my dad's advice always to me
is keep working hard.
Keep working hard.
Don't let them down.
So keep moving.
Yeah.
And what about your children?
Are they proud of what you've
accomplished?
They are.
Yes.
So, um, when you were introduced to
people, your people say you're the CEO
and you're the are the CEO of Fedex.
Are they surprised that somebody that
came from India is running this company
that is legendarily built by, uh, Fred
Smith?
I was introduced to this minister, uh,
from an African country.
He just could not digest this fact.
It was like it was like double take and
triple and.
You are the CEO.
You are the global CEO.
So there is a little bit of that
sometimes, but, uh, I think, you know,
it's, um.
It's not.
It is this.
That's rarer.
Rare at this point.
So what do you do when you're relaxing
if you're not, um, you know, looking
for, you know, where you're package wise
or something like that?
Um, what do you do?
Give them a package.
You know, you never have to look for it.
Oh, no.
Yeah.
I think for me, I mean, at this point,
either, uh, family time with tennis,
that's kind of.
You're a tennis tennis player.
So that's my, um, meditation as well as
relaxation.
And you ever play with, like, have your
employees the way you beat them?
I assume you can beat them pretty
readily.
No, I is I do we will be a we actually
have Memphis of course you know that's
all the Fedex folks.
And so we play.
But no nobody gives me a quarter on this
I can assure you that no, they're not
given up, in fact, that I would be upset
if they did.
Fred Smith came up with this idea years
ago, and obviously it's built a big
business and so forth.
But are you worried that some young Fred
Smith somewhere else is going to come up
with something that replaces your
business for us, part of the culture
that Freud drilled into our brain is
that change is the only constant.
And if you don't like change, you will
absolutely hate extinction.
And um, so we are constantly with that
mantra in place.
Now, having said that,
the physical network that we have in
place, and I keep repeating to this, as
you can pick out a package or a shipment
from any one part of the world and get
it to any other part of the world.
It it's taking us 53 years to build this
incredible network that is going to be
very, very difficult to replicate.
So unless someone is inventing it, beam
me up, Scotty machine.
And, um, you know, moving through ether,
it's.
This is going to get very, very
difficult.
So I think there are certain things that
are clear modes for us.
But, uh, then the question for us is how
do we innovate and change, continue to
keep that energy up and move forward.
All right.
So today, if somebody wants to get a job
at Fedex and rise up, what's the best
way to get a job at Fedex these days?
Well, it is, uh, it depends on what job
he wants.
And if there's someone here, you know.
No, that's not open right now.
So,
uh, but, uh, I think starting off in
Fedex at an operational, uh, side of the
house, you know, obviously we hire a lot
of people every single day, like you
said, 25 to 25,000 in the last year.
And the great thing is a lot of people
who start around as frontline careers,
I've had a fantastic career.
And in fact, uh, you know, several of
them rise to executive level positions
in this company.
And there's a long history of that.
And then, of course, the staff jobs as
well, because I feel we are in a very
exciting time period here.
And, uh, the and that's and the word's
getting around.
So the interest level is actually as
increasing.
And whether it is, you know, you know,
whether it's different functional jobs
or especially in technology and the
ability for Fedex to leverage what we
have today and have a different view on
how we can leverage technology to drive
it on.
So we are getting a lot of interest in
Fedex for that.
As I mentioned earlier, stock is up
about 73% since you took over.
So you know, probably you can't do much
better.
So would I be better not to buy the
stock now would you say or no.
I think that's that's not the way to
look at it.
It's a go.
Yeah.
You got to look at it from what's coming
next.
And, uh, so what are you going to do to
make it even more profitable?
I think so, I think our financial goals,
I told you, are very exciting and but
also, most importantly, achievable.
The transformation that's underway at
Fedex today, whether it is our network
transformation or of organizational
transformation or digital
transformation, those are real levers
for us.
And we can create now new businesses on
which layers on on top of our existing
physical business, in a way.
And so it's very exciting.
We are all excited for Fedex and we
think there's a lot more to go.
How do you spend your time as CEO?
I've thought about it carefully because
I know what the first year was like.
Uh, I mean, I realized that the most
important asset that I have is time.
So I actually sat down and thought about
and said, what's my job?
And so one, of course, is the guide, the
strategic direction of where the company
is headed.
Make sure that I have the right set of
people around me to execute, have an
execution framework, but not get
involved in every aspect of execution.
Uh, and represent the company well
internally and externally.
And once I kind of got clarified in my
own mind that this is what my job is,
then I actually went through my calendar
and I just very disciplined, you know,
put back and got, you know, some
subsegments, I would say about three out
of the five days I'm traveling.
Uh, what's the most enjoyable part of
your job?
Oh, um, by a wide margin is actually
interacting with the team members, not
the interviewing.
Like this.
That's a second.
Maybe.
Uh, no, I think it's a it's a it's a
team members, uh, they just, you know,
really an incredible set of, uh, team.
It doesn't matter where you are in the
world.
And what's the most enjoyable part?
Because we are in every part of the
world and very, very kind of, you know,
these days, I got to get up in the
morning and say a little prayer before I
look at my phone.
So, you know, we go because I don't know
what's happening.
And, uh, and so, you know, just the
unpredictability of it.
How you met your wife at Fedex.
Yeah, just in the same time frame.
And she joined Fedex about six months
after we got married.
Yeah.
You had to be a Fedex employee to be
married.
There's no other way around.
I need to have a job before she married
me.
You are now 60 years old?
Yes, 60.
You have virtually no gray hair.
Why is that?
That's a good.
That's a secret that's going to remain
with me.
Well, maybe you could whisper to me
later.
Okay,
okay.
You've done a great job for your
shareholders and your employees.
Well, and I'm sure Fred would be very
proud of what you've done.
Thank you.